A Guide to the William Anderson Civil War Letters
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
William Anderson Civil War Letters 1861-1948
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10366
76 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The William Anderson Civil War letters were given to the Library without restrictions by Miss Margaret A. Jeffries of Culpeper, Virginia, through Mr. William Jeffries of Charlottesville, Virginia, on February 7, 1980.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of seventy-six letters and related items, (1861-1864), 1883, 1948, regarding a Confederate soldier, Captain William Anderson, of Company L, Palmetto Sharpshooters, a South Carolina unit; though he was promoted to major, April 1862, the majority of these letters were written while he was a captain. Most of the letters are from Anderson to his wife, Lucretia McFall, and include descriptions of camp life and the battles of First Bull Run (Manassas), Ball's Bluff, Williamsburg, and Seven Pines (Fair Oaks).
Also included are two letters from Anderson's brother-in-law, James McFall, to Lucretia Anderson, a letter from Anderson's commanding officer, Col. J. J. Sloan, re Anderson's death of wounds received in the Seven Days' Battles and a newspaper article about Sloan. There is also a 1948 letter from the Adjutant General's Office, U. S. Army, containing information concerning Anderson's career, and a copy of the marriage certificate of Maggie Anderson (Anderson's daughter) and William Jeffries, dated 1883.
Contents List
- Series I: Letters from William Anderson to his wife
  - letter re: service of William Anderson, 1948 May 6
  - from Centreville, Va., 1861 January 26; 2 pp.
  - from Columbia, [SC], 1861 April 4; 2 pp.
  - from Columbia, SC, 1861 April 17; 1 p.
  - from Columbia, [SC], 1861 May 12; 2 pp.
  - from Columbia, SC, 1861 June 4; 2 pp. with envelope
  - from Columbia, SC, 1861 June 6; 1 pp. with envelope
  - from Richmond, [Va.], 1861 June 19; 4 pp.
  - from Camp Carolina, [Leesburg], Va., 1861 June 24; 2 pp. with envelope
  - from Camp Carolina, Leesburg, Va., 1861 June 27; 2 pp. with envelope
  - from Camp Evans, Leesburg, Va., [1861] June 30; 3 pp.
  - from Camp Evans, Leesburg, Va., 1861 July 2; 2 pp. with envelope
  - from Camp Evans, Leesburg, Va., 1861 July 9; 3 pp. with envelope
  - from Camp Fabor, Fairfax Count, Va., 1861 July 13; 2 pp. with envelope
  - from Camp Halcombe, [Fairfax Co., Va.], 1861 July 14; 2 pp.
  - from Stone Bridge, [Fairfax Co., Va.], 1861 July 24; 4 pp.
  - from Camp Pettis, Fairfax Co., Va., 1861 July 30; 3 pp.
  - from Culpeper Court House, [Va.], [1861] August 9; 3 pp.
  - from Culpeper Court House, [Va.], 1861 August 15; 3 pp. with envelope
  - from Germantown, Fairfax Co., Va., 1861 August 21; 3 pp. with envelope
  - from Germantown, Fairfax Co., Va., 1861 August 28; 3 pp.
  - from Germantown, Va., 1861 September 1; 2 pp.
  - from Germantown, Va., 1861 September 5; 3 pp. with envelope
  - from Germantown, Va., 1861 September 5; 3 pp. with envelope
  - from Germantown, Va., 1861 September 8; 4 pp. with envelope
  - from Germantown, Va., 1861 September 11; 3 pp. with envelope
  - from Germantown, Va., 1861 September 15; 4 pp.
  - from Germantown, Va., 1861 September 16; 1 pp.
  - from Germantown, Va., 1861 September 23; 4 pp.
  - from Germantown, Va., 1861 September 29; 2 pp.
  - from Germantown, Va., 1861 October 1; 3 pp. with envelope
  - from Germantown, Va., 1861 October 8; 3 pp.
  - from Germantown, Va., 1861 October 13; 4 pp.
  - from Germantown, Va., 1861 October 15; 2 pp.
  - from Camp - 4th Regt. S.C.V[olunteers], Va., 1861 October 17; 2 pp. with envelope
  - from McLean's Ford, Va., 1861 October 23; 4 pp.
  - from McLean's Ford, Va., 1861 October 28; 4 pp.
  - from McLean's Ford, Va., 1861 November 1; 2 pp.
  - from McLean's Ford, Va., 1861 November 10; 1 pp.
  - from Centreville, Va., 1861 November 13; 4 pp. with envelope
  - from Centreville, Va., 1861 November 18; 2 pp.
  - from Centreville, Va., 1861 November 23; 4 pp.
  - from Centreville, Va., 1861 December 7; 3 pp.
  - from Richmond, Va.; may have possibily been written on January 16, 1862; is dated 1862 December 16, [1861] December 16; 4 pp.
  - from Richmond, Va., 1861 Dec16; 2 pp. with envelope
  - from Centreville, Va., 1862 January 19; 2 pp.
  - from Centreville, Va., 1862 February 1; 2 pp.
  - from Centreville, Va., 1862 February 4; 1 pp.
  - from Centreville, Va., 1862 February 9; 2 pp.
  - from Centreville, Va., [1862] February 22; 4 pp.
  - from Centreville, Va., 1862 March 4; 2 pp.
  - from Centreville, Va., 1862 March 7; 2 pp.
  - from Camp at Hazel River, 1862 March 14; 1 pp.
  - from Camp Taylor, Orange Court House, Va., [1862] March 23; 3 pp.
  - from Camp Taylor, Va., 1862 April 1; 4 pp.
  - from Camp Taylor, Va., 1862 April 5; 4 pp.
  - from Richmond, Va., [1862] April 15; 1 pp.
  - from Yorktwon, Va. (w/transcript), 1862 April 18; 4 pp.
  - from Yorktown, Va., 1862 April 24; 4 pp. with envelope.
  - from Yorktown, Va., 1862 April 26; 4 pp.
  - from Yorktown, Va, 1862 May 1; 3 pp. with envelope
  - from Camp near Chickahominy River, Va., 1862 May 8; 2 p with envelope
  - from Camp near Chickahominy River, Va., [1862] May 10; 3 pp.
  - from Richmond, Va., 1862 May 23; 3 pp.
  - from Richmond, Va., 1862 May 28; 4 pp.
  - from Richmond, Va., 1862 June 2; 3 pp.
  - from Camp Jenkins, 1862 June 7; 4 pp. with envelope
  - from Richmond, Va. (w/transcript), 1862 June 10; 4 pp. with envelope
  - from Richmond, Va., 1862 June 18; 2 pp.
  - from Richmond, Va., 1862 June 23; 3 pp.
- Series II: Anderson Family Papers
  - John T. Sloan to Mrs. Lucretia Anderson, from Pendleton, [SC], 1862 July 11; 2 pp. with address leaf
  - [James] to his sister, [Mrs. William Anderson], from Morristown, Tenn. (w/transcript), 1864 February 4; 4 pp.
  - James [ ] to his sister, Mrs. William Anderson, from New Market, Tenn., 1864 February 5; 2 pp. with envelope
  - Marriage certificate of William L. Jeffries and Maggie E. Anderson, 1883 February 23; 1 pp.
  - [ ] O'Hara to Linora C. Hubbard, enclosing poetry, n.d.; 4 pp.
  - Obituary of J. B. E. Sloan, n.d.